让我们来看看这些例子。
Let's go through these examples.
我们将返回，结果，它就在屏幕上。
We'll circle back, it turns out, it's right here on the screen.
这是正确的end。
This is the proper endo.
我之前有点糊涂。
I got a little confused before.
原因是，如果，我们之后会绕回去，但是
The reason was, if, we'll circle back afterwards, but
我会告诉你为什么我感到困惑以及为什么这有效。
I'll show you why I got confused and why this works.
所以让我们回到我们的第一个练习，
So let's go down to our first exercise,
我们要把普通的 HTML 变成 JSX 风格的 HTML。
we're gonna turn normal HTML into the JSX style HTML.
我们要欺骗这个。
We're gonna cheat on this one.
它实际上不会正常工作，但仅用于示例目的。
It's not actually gonna work right but it's just for example purposes here.
所以，我们有endo，我们有一堆从字符串到字符串的函数，太棒了。
So, we have endo, we have a bunch of functions from string to string, terrific.
我们可以使用endo来重写它。
We can rewrite this using endo.
在我潜入之前，有人对此有任何疑问或障碍吗？
Did anybody have any questions or snags on this one before I dive in,
当我们这样做时，我可以解决。
I could address while we do it.
都好？好吧，那么，
All good? All right, so,
好吧，我们做的第一件事就是将这些放入endos，对吗？
well the first thing we do is just put these in endos, right?
我可以说 HTML 的结束，
I can say endo of HTML for,
我们将把它与这个结尾结合起来，
we'll concat that with the endo of this one,
我们将在本节末尾连接它，依此类推。
and we'll concat that at the endo of this one, and so on.
这里发生了什么？
And what's happening here?
这是一种方式，我们会用另一种方式重做，但我们还没有运行它。
This is one way, we'll redo it another way, but we haven't run it yet.
所以我们必须在 HTML 上运行它，看看它是否通过。
So we have to run it on the HTML and see if that passes.
确实如此，棒极了。
It does, terrific.
所以它只是通过幺半群捕获函数组合。
So it's just capturing function composition via monoids.
由于函数总是返回相同的输入类型和相同的输出类型，
Since the functions always return the same inputs type and same output type,
我们可以毫不费力地组合类型，从来没有类型错误。
we can effortlessly compose the types, never had a type error.
所以我们也可以说，如果我们要把它放在一个列表中，对吗？
So we also alternatively say, if we're gonna throw this on a list, right?
清单，砰。
List of, bam.
而且它在完整地图上并不重要。
And also it kind of doesn't really matter on the full map is.
有点领先于我自己，对于地图end，
Kinda ahead of myself sort of, for map endo,
我们将给它endo.empty，最后用HTML 运行它。
and we'll give it the endo.empty and finally run it with the HTML.
怎么样？
How's that?
没有用，列表没有定义。
Didn't work, list is not defined.
我提示了吗，没有带入列表。
Did I prompt, didn't bring in list.
好吧，没关系。
Okay, that's fine.
[笑]我们可以换一种方式，
[LAUGH] We could do it a different way,
我们可以把它扔到一个数组中并减少它。
we can just throw it in an array and reduce it.
如果我们没有可用的完整地图，我们可以做一个reduce，好吗？
If we don't have full map at our disposal, we could just do a reduce, all right?
一个 acc 和一个 x。
An acc and an x.
我们将 x 放在 end 中，然后有一个东西
We'll put the x in the endo and there's a something
提醒我们，就像猎犬帮派一样，将 x 放在 end 中。
reminds us that like a bloodhound gang line, put the x in the endo.
[笑] 我把它连起来。
[LAUGH] l concat that.
那么这里发生了什么？
So what's happening here?
&gt;&gt; 您提供了额外的括号。
&gt;&gt; You've given extra parentheses.
&gt;&gt; 是的。
&gt;&gt; Yes.
&gt;&gt; 打开一。
&gt;&gt; Opening one.
&gt;&gt; 就是这样。
&gt;&gt; There it is.
巴姆，好吧。
Bam, all right.
我们走了，传球。
And there we go, passes.
所以，再一次，这是所有折叠地图都拿走了，对吧？
So, again, this is all fold map took away, right?
这就像一条线。
It's like a one line.
我不必为此导入库。
I didn't have to import a library for that.
我只是因为真的需要推广我的图书馆。
I just do because really need to promote my libraries.
是的，我才明白。
Yeah, I'm just getting it.
这正是你会一直在其他语言中看到的。
It's just what you're gonna see in other languages all the time.
所以我想模仿那个。
So I wanted to mimic that.
那真的不是关于图书馆。
That's it's really not about the library.
这是关于通用接口的，太酷了，完成了。
It's about common Interfaces, so cool, done.
它把这件事变成了这件事。
And it turned this thing into this thing.
[笑] 如果你注意到顺序并不重要，是吗？
[LAUGH] And if you notice the order doesn't really matter, does it?
这是你签署的合同的一部分。
And that's kind of part of the contract you're kinda signing up for a little bit.
它正在组合它们，但它是，因为它总是相同的类型，
It is composing them, but it's, since it's always the same type,
我的意思是顺序往往无关紧要，好吧。
I mean the order tends to not matter, okay.
让我们进入谓词。
Let's go into predicates.
现在，所以这个，我们将在这里讨论一些很酷的东西。
Now, so this, we're gonna get into some cool stuff here.
当我们在最后一个减速器示例中离开时，我们将反对 map。
We're gonna contra map as we left off in the last example of reducers.
所以让我们继续编写谓词，我们将接收一个函数，
So let's go ahead and write predicate, we'll take in a function,
谓词函数，往往会调用这些运行。
predicate function, tend to call these run.
并遵循我们为公开运行所做的相同模式。
And follow the same kind of pattern we've been doing for expose run.
我们在这里要做的就是说，反对地图。
And what we'll do here is just say, contra map.
由于谓词是 a，它需要一个返回布尔值的函数，对吗？
Since predicate is a, it takes a function that returns a Boolean, right?
所以我无法映射它。
So I cannot map it.
我不能把布尔值变成另一回事。
I can't turn the Boolean into another thing.
它不再是谓词函数。
It wouldn't be a predicate function anymore.
那只会破坏建模谓词的整个想法。
That would just ruin the whole idea of modeling predicates.
所以我要做的就是反对地图，给自己一个机会，
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna contra map, and give myself an opportunity,
提前一个小钩子来击中我们的价值，
a little hook beforehand to hit our value coming in,
x 和 f，在它实际运行之前。
x with the f, before it actually runs.
所以让我们看看这里发生了什么。
So let's see what's happening here.
所以我们有一张 contra 地图，我们也需要连接。
So we have a contra map, and we need to concat too.
没关系。
That's fine.
我们如何连接两个谓词？
How do we concat two predicates?
康卡特，我们再拿一个。
Concat, we take another one.
而且，所以我们在这里有一个谓词。
And, so we have a predicate here.
我们可以，抱歉，这是违禁地图，忘记跑了。
And we could, sorry, this is contra map, forgot to run.
所以这里出了点问题。
So something's wrong here.
我会运行它的价值。
I will run the value of that.
好的，很酷。
Okay, cool.
你看我是怎么错过的。
Do you see how I missed that.
我们要在 x 上点击 f 并且
We're gonna hit the f on the x and
在我们实际运行它之前转换值。
transform the value before we actually run it.
好的，在这里连接，我们要做的是说，
All right, in concat here, what we're gonna do here is say,
好吧，如果我运行它，它会给我一个布尔值，我们还有另一个，对吧？
well, if I run this, so it'll give me a Boolean and we have another one, right?
我不知道为什么那会过去[笑]这可能不好，但是
I don't know why that's passing [LAUGH] that's probably not good, but
无论如何，让我这样做。
let me do this anyway.
我们会说我们有另一个带有运行功能的
We're gonna say we have some other one with a run function and
我们可以连接另一个运行。
we can just concat that other run.
我认为我们现在必须决定是否或
And I think we have to decide right now whether or
我们不想在我们的谓词函数中返回任何或所有是免费的。
not we wanna return any or all within our predicate functions are free.
我们只想修一个。
We just wanna fix one.
我们为什么不直接说和。
Why don't we just say and.
这，人们看到它是如何工作的了吗？
This, did people see how that works?
基本上，如果我运行我的谓词函数将返回真或假。
Basically, if I run my predicate function is gonna return a true or false.
如果我运行另一个，它会返回真或假。
If I run the other one, it's gonna return a true or false.
现在我有一个谓词函数，它告诉我它们都是真还是假。
And now I have a predicate function that tells me they're both true or both false.
我可以决定使它成为一个或。
I could decide to make it an or.
或者我实际上可以说不，它会在我内部返回另一个幺半群。
Or I can actually say no, it returns me another monoid inside.
现在我连接了这两个，但我们并没有真正设置它来做到这一点。
And now I concat those two but we didn't really set this up to do that.
所以让我们把它修好，它就过去了。
So let's just fix it to and it passes.
就这么过去了，倒是有些担心。
It was a little worrying that it passed this way.
所以我可能只是写了一个不好的例子，但它应该是这样的。
So I probably just wrote a bad example, but this is what it should look like.
[笑] 但是，如果你看这里的例子，
[LAUGH] But yeah, if you look at the example here,
我们在 x 到达之前获取它的长度。
we're grabbing the length of x before it gets here.
然后我们问，它是否以 s 开头。
And then we're asking, if it starts with s.
所以我们把这些都变成了，好吧，看起来像，
So we're transforming each of these into, all right, looks like,
是我们问的是整个数组的长度，而不是每个数组的长度。
is that we're asking about the entire arrays length not each one's length.
这就是错误的原因吗？
Is that why it was wrong?
好吧，无论如何，谓词看起来很棒。
Well, in any case, that's predicate looks great.
我们可以进一步深入了解为什么会通过。
We can dig in further into why that passed.
是的。
Yeah.
&gt;&gt; 你能不能再给一下像反对地图的高级定义 -
&gt;&gt; Could you just give like the high level definition of contra map again with the-
&gt;&gt; 是的，所以这里的想法，
&gt;&gt; Yeah, so here's the idea,
是这样吗，我有这个谓词吗？
is that like, I have this predicate right?
来，看看这个，对吧？
Here, look at this one, right?
我有这个谓词说，
I've got this predicate that says,
我们称之为大于四。
let's call it greater than four.
这个谓词函数需要一个数字，对。
And this predicate function takes a number, right.
我还有这个其他谓词函数
And I have this other predicate function
需要一个字符串，const sStart。
that takes a string, const sStart.
[笑] 所以它以 s 开头，好酷。
[LAUGH] So it starts with s, okay cool.
所以我有两个谓词函数。
So I have two predicate functions.
这个需要一个字符串，这个需要一个数字。
This one takes a string, this one takes a number.
我想做的是遍历我的结果
And what I wanted to do is run through my results and
过滤所有满足这两个谓词的字符串。
filter all these strings that satisfy both predicates.
但是我不想将字符串传递给需要数字的东西，对吗？
But I don't want to pass a string to the thing that takes a number, right?
所以我能做的就是反映射它，我们把它转换成它的长度。
So what I can do is contra map that it, we transform it into its length.
但我不想在定义中这样做。
But I don't want to do that in the definition.
当我将两者结合起来说时，我可以在调用函数中做到这一点，
I can do that at the calling function when I'm combining the two to say like,
你知道吗？
you know what?
我有一个钩子可以
I have a hook to be able to
实际上更改此函数并仍将其传递到同一个过滤器中。
actually change this function and still pass it into the same filter.
然后这让我有能力编写一个过滤器
And then that gives me the ability to write one filter that just kind of
组合所有这些谓词并在它们到达之前转换它们。
combines all these predicates and transforms them before they get there.
所以这是具体情况，但是
So that's the specific case, but
一般情况是，通常当您将这些功能组合成一个时，
the general case is that typically when you're combining these functions into one,
他们可能会采取不同的论点，它会给你一个改变它的钩子。
they might take different arguments and it gives you a hook to kind of change it.
这是用例，对吧？
And this is the use case, right?
就像这是在库中预定义的，我想在那里使用它。
Like this is predefined in a library and I want to use that there.
这回答了问题还是你还有一些 -
Did that answer the question or are you still have some-
&gt;&gt; 不不，这很清楚。
&gt;&gt; No no, that's that's pretty clear.
&gt;&gt; 酷。
&gt;&gt; Cool.
只是如果，我们只是让我们知道它被称为逆变函子，如果你
Just if, we just so we're aware it's called a contravariant functor if you
有反向映射，逆变，反向映射。
have contra map, contravariant, contra map.
如果我们有 contra map 和 map，它被称为 profunctor。
If we have contra map and map, it's called a profunctor.
您可以更改输入和输出。
You can change the input and the output.
这有点像连接器的小东西。
It's kind of like a little connector thing.
所以 profunctor 定义了两者，逆变函子做一个和
And so profunctors define both, contravariant functors does one and
只是函子或其他只是地图 我们有这个有趣的小图形。
just functors or the other just map We have this little fun graphic.
[笑]如果有人想过夜，
[LAUGH] If anybody wants to spend a night,
给自己倒一杯烈酒，通读一遍。
pour yourself stiff drink, read through that.
但就在那里。
But that's there.
如果你想看看那里，它在幻想土地数字中。
It's in the fantasy land figures if you want to take a look there.
好的，回到我们的例子。
Okay, back to our our example.
所以在练习三，这是最后一个练习。
So on exercise three, which is the last exercise.
我们在这里要做的是说，
What we're gonna do here is say,
使用matchesAny 谓词重写，因此它建立在前一个谓词的基础上。
rewrite using the matchesAny predicate, so it builds on the previous one.
所以如果你没有得到上一个，这一个会更难。
So if you didn't get the previous one, this one will be harder.
这个想法是我们有matchesAny，它只是一个普通的字符串匹配和
The idea is that we have matchesAny, which is just a normal string match and
然后我们有匹配的 IP，即谓词版本。
then we have matching IP, the predicate version of that.
我们只是包装了matchesAny 并将其放入谓词中。
We just wrapped matchesAny and put it in a predicate.
所以现在谓词是一个函数，当你调用 run 时，
So now predicate is a function which takes, when you call run,
它需要那个字符串。
it takes that string.
所以你想用matchesAny IP运行这些。
So you wanna run these with matchesAny IP.
既然我们想利用 concat 和 contra map，我们可以，
And since we wanna take advantage of concat and contra map, we can,
给我们一个提示，让我们快速了解正在发生的事情。
kind of give us a hint as to, let's just give a quick idea of what's happening is.
我在这里调用文件的扩展名，并且
I'm calling the extension on the file here, and
我正在那里调用文件中的内容。
I'm calling contents on the file there.
并将它们与
And combine them with and so let's leave that alone for a second and
只需在它下面用matchesAny IP写同样的东西。
just write the same thing under it with matchesAny IP.
所以现在我有了它，我实际上可以反对地图扩展，对吗？
So now that I have that, I can actually contra map extension, right?
然后我可以连接而不是调用 and，用另一个谓词 and
And then I can concat instead of calling and, with another predicate and
这个需要内容，所以我可以映射那个x.contents。
this one takes contents so I can contra map that one x.contents.
所以我猜文件，归档内容，然后我们必须运行它。
So I guess the file, file the contents and then we have to run it.
用文件运行它。
Run it with the file.
看看能不能通过。
See if that passes.
它没有，可能有参数语法错误。
It does not, probably have a argument syntax error.
我们走了。
There we go.
几乎就在那里，在扩展上拆分未定义。
And almost there, split of undefined on extension.
那么让我们看看那里发生了什么。
So let's see what happened there.
扩展名获取文件，扩展名是什么样的？。
Extension takes the file, what does extension look like?.
File.name.split，好的。
File.name.split, all right.
每个文件都有一个名称。
Each file has a name.
有人看到任何问题吗？
Anybody see any issues?
我们反对将扩展名与这个扩展名进行映射。
We're contra mapping the extension concacting it with this one.
所以在这里我关闭了 concat 并且我正在映射内容。
So here I closed the concat and I'm conra mapping the contents.
如果我把它移到外面，现在它应该可以工作了。
If I move this on the outside, now it should work.
所以让我们看一下，让我把这个稍微分解成那个。
So let's take a look, allow me, just kind of break this down a little bit to that.
那么，我们看到我们有这个功能吗？
So, are we seeing we have this function and
然后将它与该函数连接起来，然后我们运行它。
then concatenate it with that function, and then we're running it.
我犯了一个错误，我可以将它与它连接起来
I made a mistake where I can concated it with that and
然后反对映射整个事情。
then contra map the whole thing.
因为每次我连接两个东西时，我都会得到一个新东西，对吧？
Because every time I concat two things, I get a new thing back, right?
这实际上对建筑有很大的影响。
This actually has big, big implications for architecture.
也就是说，如果你看一个正常的应用程序，
Which is that if you look at a normal app that's normal,
一个典型的日常 JavaScript 应用程序或 Ruby 或 Java 或
a typical everyday JavaScript application or Ruby or Java or
无论你想看什么，它都会有很多类型和很多值。
whatever you want to look at, its gonna have a lot of types and a lot of values.
你最终会得到适配器和类型转换
And you end up with adapters and type transformations and
你必须做很多事情才能把东西塞在一起。
a lot of stuff that you have to do to kind of plug things together.
然而，他们只是喜欢很多片段，这是你保留的这种附加流
And yet a lot of pieces they just kind of, it's this additive flow where you keep
向系统添加新的部分，然后你必须处理它们。
adding new pieces to the system and then you kind of have to deal with them.
使用幺半群，你有一个片段，你只需将它们组合成同一个片段。
With monoid, you have one piece and you just combine them into the same piece.
所以你不需要适配器，你只需不断组合，你就会得到一件事
And so you don't need adapters, you just keep combining and you get one thing back
而不是这种复合物或将事物锁在一起的新类型。
instead of this composite thing or new types that kind of latch things together.
所以，通过将我们的类型规范化为谓词并说我们要得到，
So, by normalizing our types into predicates and saying we're gonna get,
提供一堆可比较的谓词，然后将它们组合起来。
provide a bunch of compasable predicates and then combine them.
你没有在你的系统中引入任何新概念，
You're not introducing any new concepts in your system,
你只是不断地把它粉碎成一件事。
you're just continually smashing it back into one thing.
好的，是的，让我们在这里回顾一下我的小问题。
Okay, yeah, let's take a look back at my little issue here.
我们只是尝试做，比方说，我想为 end 提供一个空字符串。
We're just trying to do, let's say, I wanna provide endo with an empty string.
我很喜欢，坚持下去，对吧？
I was very like, stuck on that, right?
我想，我，这些是字符串函数
I was like, I, these are string functions and
我需要做空的end，我没有空的。
I need to do empty endo and I didn't have empty.
那么为什么它不能使用空字符串呢？
So why wouldn't it work with an empty string?
好吧，事实证明，endo 稍后会得到它的论点。
Well, it turns out that endo gets its argument later.
Endo 是一个函数，当你调用 run 时，
Endo was a function that when you call run,
那是它得到论证的时候，对吧？
that's when it gets its argument, right?
和恒等函数，因为它是一个从相同类型到
And the identity function, since it's a function from the same type to
同样的类型，这里又是恒等函数。
the same type, here it is, again, identity function.
它派上用场了，对吧？
It's coming in handy, right?
它说，好吧，好吧，我们就从你开始的地方开始
And it says, okay, well, we'll just take what you started with and
使，有效地使空值。
make, effectively make that the empty value.
所以后来才来。
So it comes later.
这就是我被绊倒的地方。
That's where I got little tripped up.
所以在那里，所以内空是完全没问题的。
So there, so endo empty is totally fine.
它持有一个函数而不是一个空字符串。
It's holding a function not an empty string.
所以，然后如果我们看看这一切，如果我跑的话，效果会很好
So, and then if we look at all this, it works out just fine if I run
节点函数建模为零，我们得到了我们的Hello 东西。
node function modeling zero, we get this our Hello thing.
稍后我将讨论这个问题，但是是的，完全有效。
I'm gonna talk about this in a second but yeah, totally works.